<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<PubmedArticleSet><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">32205204</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2020</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>14</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1872-7913</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>56</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2020</Year><Month>Jul</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of antimicrobial agents</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Antimicrob Agents</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>RETRACTED: Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>105949</StartPage><MedlinePgn>105949</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0924-8579(20)30099-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine have been found to be efficient on SARS-CoV-2, and reported to be efficient in Chinese COV-19 patients. We evaluate the effect of hydroxychloroquine on respiratory viral loads.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENTS AND METHODS">French Confirmed COVID-19 patients were included in a single arm protocol from early March to March 16<sup>th</sup>, to receive 600mg of hydroxychloroquine daily and their viral load in nasopharyngeal swabs was tested daily in a hospital setting. Depending on their clinical presentation, azithromycin was added to the treatment. Untreated patients from another center and cases refusing the protocol were included as negative controls. Presence and absence of virus at Day6-post inclusion was considered the end point.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Six patients were asymptomatic, 22 had upper respiratory tract infection symptoms and eight had lower respiratory tract infection symptoms. Twenty cases were treated in this study and showed a significant reduction of the viral carriage at D6-post inclusion compared to controls, and much lower average carrying duration than reported in the litterature for untreated patients. Azithromycin added to hydroxychloroquine was significantly more efficient for virus elimination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">Despite its small sample size, our survey shows that hydroxychloroquine treatment is significantly associated with viral load reduction/disappearance in COVID-19 patients and its effect is reinforced by azithromycin.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="UNLABELLED">This article has been retracted: please see Elsevier Policy on Article Withdrawal (https://www.elsevier.com/locate/withdrawalpolicy). Concerns have been raised regarding this article, the substance of which relate to the articles' adherence to Elsevier's publishing ethics policies and the appropriate conduct of research involving human participants, as well as concerns raised by three of the authors themselves regarding the article's methodology and conclusions. Elsevier's Research Integrity and Publishing Ethics Team, in collaboration with the journal's co-owner, the International Society of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy (ISAC), and with guidance from an impartial field expert acting in the role of an independent Publishing Ethics Advisor, Dr. Jim Gray, Consultant Microbiologist at the Birmingham Children's and Women's Hospitals, U.K., conducted an investigation and determined that the below points constituted cause for retraction: • The journal has been unable to confirm whether any of the patients for this study were accrued before ethical approval had been obtained. The ethical approval dates for this article are stated as being 5th and 6th of March 2020 (ANSM and CPP respectively), while the article states that recruitment began in “early March”. The 17th author, Prof. Philippe Brouqui, has confirmed that the start date for patient accrual was 6th March 2020. The journal has not been able to establish whether all patients could have entered into the study in time for the data to have been analysed and included in the manuscript prior to its submission on the 20th March 2020, nor whether all patients were enrolled in the study upon admission as opposed to having been hospitalised for some time before starting the treatment described in the article. Additionally, the journal has not been able to establish whether there was equipoise between the study patients and the control patients. • The journal has not been able to establish whether the subjects in this study should have provided informed consent to receive azithromycin as part of the study. The journal has concluded that that there is reasonable cause to conclude that azithromycin was not considered standard care at the time of the study. The 17th author, Prof. Philippe Brouqui has attested that azithromycin treatment was not, at the time of the study, an experimental treatment but a possible treatment for, or preventative measure against, bacterial superinfections of viral pneumonia as described in section 2.4 of the article, and as such the treatment should be categorised as standard care that would not require informed consent. This does not fully address the journal's concerns around the use of azithromycin in the study. In section 3.1 of the article, it is stated that six patients received azithromycin to prevent (rather than treat) bacterial superinfection. All of these were amongst the patients who also received hydroxychloroquine (HCQ). None of the control patients are reported to have received azithromycin. This would indicate that only patients in the HCQ arm received azithromycin, all of whom were in one center. The recommendations for use of macrolides in France at the time the study was conducted indicate that azithromycin would not have been a logical agent to use as first-line prophylaxis against pneumonia due to the frequency of macrolide resistance amongst bacteria such as pneumococci. These two points suggest that azithromycin would not have been standard practice across southern France at the time the study was conducted and would have required informed consent. • Three of the authors of this article, Dr. Johan Courjon, Prof. Valérie Giordanengo, and Dr. Stéphane Honoré have contacted the journal to assert their opinion that they have concerns regarding the presentation and interpretation of results in this article and have stated they no longer wish to see their names associated with the article. • Author Prof. Valérie Giordanengo informed the journal that while the PCR tests administered in Nice were interpreted according to the recommendations of the national reference center, it is believed that those carried out in Marseille were not conducted using the same technique or not interpreted according to the same recommendations, which in her opinion would have resulted in a bias in the analysis of the data. This raises concerns as to whether the study was partially conducted counter to national guidelines at that time. The 17th author, Prof. Philippe Brouqui has attested that the PCR methodology was explained in reference 17 of the article. However, the article referred to by reference 17 describes several diagnostic approaches that were used (one PCR targeting the envelope protein only; another targeting the spike protein; and three commercially produced systems by QuantiNova, Biofire, and FTD). This reference does not clarify how the results were interpreted. It has also been noted during investigation of these concerns that only 76% (19/25) of patients were viral culture positive, resulting in uncertainty in the interpretation of PCR reports as has been raised by Prof. Giordanengo. As part of the investigation, the corresponding author was contacted and asked to provide an explanation for the above concerns. No response has been received within the deadline provided by the journal. Responses were received by the 3rd and 17th authors, Prof. Philippe Parola and Prof. Philippe Brouqui, respectively, and were reviewed as part of the investigation. These two authors, in addition to 1st author Dr. Philippe Gautret, 13th author Prof. Philippe Colson, and 15th author Prof. Bernard La Scola, disagreed with the retraction and dispute the grounds for it. Having followed due process and concluded the aforementioned investigation and based on the recommendation of Dr. Jim Gray acting in his capacity as independent Publishing Ethics Advisor, the co-owners of the journal (Elsevier and ISAC) have therefore taken the decision to retract the article.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2020. Published by Elsevier B.V.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gautret</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, AP-HM, SSA, VITROME, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lagier</LastName><ForeName>Jean-Christophe</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Parola</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, AP-HM, SSA, VITROME, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hoang</LastName><ForeName>Van Thuan</ForeName><Initials>VT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, AP-HM, SSA, VITROME, Marseille, France; Thai Binh University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Thai Binh, Viet Nam.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meddeb</LastName><ForeName>Line</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mailhe</LastName><ForeName>Morgane</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doudier</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Courjon</LastName><ForeName>Johan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Infectiologie, Hôpital de l'Archet, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice, Nice, France; Université Côte d'Azur, Nice, France; U1065, Centre Méditerranéen de Médecine Moléculaire, C3M, Virulence Microbienne et Signalisation Inflammatoire, INSERM, Nice, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giordanengo</LastName><ForeName>Valérie</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Virology, Biological and Pathological Center, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice, 06200 Nice, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vieira</LastName><ForeName>Vera Esteves</ForeName><Initials>VE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tissot Dupont</LastName><ForeName>Hervé</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Honoré</LastName><ForeName>Stéphane</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service Pharmacie, Hôpital Timone, AP-HM, Marseille, France; Laboratoire de Pharmacie Clinique, Aix Marseille Université, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Colson</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chabrière</LastName><ForeName>Eric</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>La Scola</LastName><ForeName>Bernard</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rolain</LastName><ForeName>Jean-Marc</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brouqui</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Raoult</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>IHU-Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France; Aix Marseille Univ, IRD, APHM, MEPHI, Marseille, France. Electronic address: Didier.raoult@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016430">Clinical Trial</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016441">Retracted Publication</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Antimicrob Agents</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9111860</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0924-8579</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>4QWG6N8QKH</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D006886">Hydroxychloroquine</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>83905-01-5</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D017963">Azithromycin</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Ann Rheum Dis. 2020 Jun;79(6):e60. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2020-217501.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32295788</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Oncologist. 2020 Jun;25(6):455-457. doi: 10.1634/theoncologist.2020-0313.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32304334</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Eur J Intern Med. 2020 Jul;77:139-140. doi: 10.1016/j.ejim.2020.04.057.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32414641</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Kaohsiung J Med Sci. 2020 Aug;36(8):660. doi: 10.1002/kjm2.12249.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32533592</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>J Neurol Sci. 2020 Aug 15;415:116972. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2020.116972.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32534369</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>J Glob Antimicrob Resist. 2020 Sep;22:680-684. doi: 10.1016/j.jgar.2020.06.016.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32622008</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>S Afr Med J. 2020 Apr 02;110(5):12903. doi: 10.7196/SAMJ.2020.v110i5.14761.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32657706</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020 Jul;56(1):106063. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106063.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32674928</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Am J Epidemiol. 2020 Nov 2;189(11):1443-1444. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwaa151.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32685975</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Travel Med Infect Dis. 2020 Sep - Oct;37:101826. doi: 10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101826.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32739472</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Mayo Clin Proc. 2020 Sep;95(9):1842-1844. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2020.06.037.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32861327</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Rev Peru Med Exp Salud Publica. 2020 Apr-Jun;37(2):383-384. doi: 10.17843/rpmesp.2020.372.5465.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32876237</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2020 Oct 1;108(2):333-336. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2020.08.001.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32890500</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>J Patient Saf. 2021 Jan 1;17(1):e43-e44. doi: 10.1097/PTS.0000000000000795.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">33074933</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Respir Med. 2021 Jun;182:106380. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2021.106380.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">33930690</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Nature. 2021 Jun;594(7861):17-18. doi: 10.1038/d41586-021-01430-z.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">34045759</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="RetractionIn"><RefSource>Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2025 Jan;65(1):107416. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2024.107416.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">39730229</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Account Res. 2026 Apr;33(3):2530085. doi: 10.1080/08989621.2025.2530085.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">41042204</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017963" MajorTopicYN="N">Azithromycin</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="Y">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073640" MajorTopicYN="Y">Betacoronavirus</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018352" MajorTopicYN="N">Coronavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="Y">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004359" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Therapy, Combination</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006886" MajorTopicYN="N">Hydroxychloroquine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="Y">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011024" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumonia, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="Y">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016133" MajorTopicYN="N">Polymerase Chain Reaction</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019562" MajorTopicYN="N">Viral Load</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000093485" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Drug Treatment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">2019-nCoV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Azithromycin</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical trial</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Hydroxychloroquine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0924-8579(20)30099-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lai C.C., Shih T.P., Ko W.C., Tang H.J., Hsueh P.R. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19): The epidemic and the challenges. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020 Feb 17 doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105924. [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32081636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L.S., Wang Y.R., Ye D.W., Liu Q.Q. A review of the 2019 Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) based on current evidence”. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020 [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7434381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32826129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Director-General's opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19 - 11 March 2020. [https://www.who.int/dg/speeches/detail/who-director-general-s-opening-remarks-at-the-media-briefing-on-covid-19---11-march-2020]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z., McGoogan J.M. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. JAMA. 2020 Feb 24 doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.2648. [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santé Publique France. Infection au nouveau Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2), COVID-19, France et Monde [https://www.santepubliquefrance.fr/maladies-et-traumatismes/maladies-et-infections-respiratoires/infection-a-coronavirus/articles/infection-au-nouveau-coronavirus-sars-cov-2-covid-19-france-et-monde]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colson P., Rolain J.M., Raoult D. Chloroquine for the 2019 novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020 Feb 15 doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105923. [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.105923</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7134866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32070753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colson P., Rolain J.M., Lagier J.C., Brouqui P., Raoult D. Chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine as available weapons to fight COVID-19. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2020 [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7135139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32145363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M., Cao R., Zhang L., Yang X., Liu J., Xu M. Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in vitro. Cell Res. 2020:10–0282.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7054408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32020029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao J., Tian Z., Yang X. Breakthrough: Chloroquine phosphate has shown apparent efficacy in treatment of COVID-19 associated pneumonia in clinical studies. Biosci Trends. 2020 Feb 19 doi: 10.5582/bst.2020.01047. [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5582/bst.2020.01047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32074550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinese Clinical Trial Registry. http://www.chictr.org.cn/searchproj.aspx?title=%E6%B0%AF%E5%96%B9&amp;officialname=&amp;subjectid=&amp;secondaryid=&amp;applier=&amp;studyleader=&amp;ethicalcommitteesanction=&amp;sponsor=&amp;studyailment=&amp;studyailmentcode=&amp;studytype=0&amp;studystage=0&amp;studydesign=0&amp;minstudyexecutetime=&amp;maxstudyexecutetime=&amp;recruitmentstatus=0&amp;gender=0&amp;agreetosign=&amp;secsponsor=&amp;regno=&amp;regstatus=0&amp;country=&amp;province=&amp;city=&amp;institution=&amp;institutionlevel=&amp;measure=&amp;intercode=&amp;sourceofspends=&amp;createyear=0&amp;isuploadrf=&amp;whetherpublic=&amp;btngo=btn&amp;verifycode=&amp;page=1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Multicenter collaboration group of Department of Science and Technology of Guangdong Province and Health Commission of Guangdong Province for chloroquine in the treatment of novel coronavirus pneumonia Expert consensus on chloroquine phosphate for the treatment of novel coronavirus pneumonia] Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi. 2020 Mar 12;43(3):185–188. doi: 10.3760/cma.j.issn.1001-0939.2020.03.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3760/cma.j.issn.1001-0939.2020.03.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32164085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biot C., Daher W., Chavain N., Fandeur T., Khalife J., Dive D. Design and synthesis of hydroxyferroquine derivatives with antimalarial and antiviral activities. J Med Chem. 2006;49:2845–2849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16640347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marmor M.F., Kellner U., Lai T.Y., Melles R.B., Mieler W.F., American Academy of Ophthalmology Recommendations on Screening for Chloroquine and Hydroxychloroquine Retinopathy (2016 Revision) Ophthalmology. Jun 2016;123(6):1386–1394. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.01.058. Epub 2016 Mar 16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.01.058</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26992838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao X., Ye F., Zhang M., Cui C., Huang B., Niu P. In Vitro Antiviral Activity and Projection of Optimized Dosing Design of Hydroxychloroquine for the Treatment of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Clin Infect Dis. 2020 Mar 9 doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa237. pii: ciaa237[Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciaa237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raoult D., Houpikian P., Tissot Dupont H., Riss J.M., Arditi-Djiane J., Brouqui P. Treatment of Q fever endocarditis: comparison of 2 regimens containing doxycycline and ofloxacin or hydroxychloroquine. Arch Intern Med. 1999 Jan 25;159(2):167–173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9927100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lagier J.C., Raoult D. Whipple's disease and Tropheryma whipplei infections: when to suspect them and how to diagnose and treat them. Curr Opin Infect Dis. Dec 2018;31(6):463–470. doi: 10.1097/QCO.0000000000000489. [x] Expert consensus on chloroquine phosphate for the treatment of novel coronavirus pneumonia. Zhonghua Jie He He Hu Xi Za Zhi. 2020 Mar 12;43(3):185-188. doi: 10.3760/cma.j.issn.1001-0939.2020.03.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QCO.0000000000000489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30299363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amrane S., Tissot-Dupont H., Doudier B., Eldin C., Hocquart M., Mailhe M. Rapid viral diagnosis and ambulatory management of suspected COVID-19 cases presenting at the infectious diseases referral hospital in Marseille, France, - January 31st to March 1st, 2020: A respiratory virus snapshot. Travel Med Infect Dis. 2020 [Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armstrong N., Richez M., Raoult D., Chabriere E. Simultaneous UHPLC-UV analysis of hydroxychloroquine, minocycline and doxycycline from serum samples for the therapeutic drug monitoring of Q fever and Whipple's disease. J. Chromatogr. B Analyt. Technol. Biomed. Life Sci. 2017;1060:166–172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28622620</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou F., Yu T., Du R., Fan G., Liu Y., Liu Z. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020 Mar 11 doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30566-3. pii: S0140-6736(20)30566-3[Epub ahead of print]</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30566-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retallack H., Di Lullo E., Arias C., Knopp K.A., Laurie M.T., Sandoval-Espinosa C. Zika virus cell tropism in the developing human brain and inhibition by azithromycin. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016 Dec 13;113(50):14408–14413. Epub 2016 Nov 29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5167169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27911847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madrid P.B., Panchal R.G., Warren T.K., Shurtleff A.C., Endsley A.N., Green C.E., Kolokoltsov A. Evaluation of Ebola Virus Inhibitors for Drug Repurposing. ACS Infect Dis. 2015 Jul 10;1(7):317–326. doi: 10.1021/acsinfecdis.5b00030. Epub 2015 May 11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1021/acsinfecdis.5b00030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27622822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bosseboeuf E., Aubry M., Nhan T., de Pina J.J., Rolain J.M., Raoult D. Azithromycin inhibits the replication of Zika virus. J Antivirals Antiretrovirals. 2018;10(1):6–11. doi: 10.4172/1948-5964.1000173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4172/1948-5964.1000173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bacharier L.B., Guilbert T.W., Mauger D.T., Boehmer S., Beigelman A., Fitzpatrick A.M. Early administration of azithromycin and prevention of severe lower respiratory tract illnesses in preschool children with a history of such illnesses: A randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2015 Nov 17;314(19):2034–2044. doi: 10.1001/jama.2015.13896.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2015.13896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4757487</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26575060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>